Natalie Spiska: Alright, perfect. If you could just start by giving a general overview of what you currently use in your golf program, including any sort of, like, wearable technology, stats websites, trackmen, indoor facilities, that sort of stuff.
Coach: Sure.
Coach: So, from an individual standpoint, I know several of the players, they have their individual technology, like their WHOO, or whatever those things are. That's more like health and fitness. From a tech… from a team tech perspective.
Coach: We have both, a Trackman simulator that works indoors and outdoors.
Coach: So, we have an indoor facility with a large hitting area, we have a screen with the projector, and that basically takes up the bulk of our winter training. And then the trackman, you can switch it from indoor to outdoor mode, and the guys will take it outside once the weather's nice enough.
Coach: And then this past winter, we just had PuttView, technology installed. I don't know if you're familiar with that. So in our, in our indoor, simulator room, half of it's TrackMan, half of it's PuttView. That is really the extent of the technology that we utilize. We used to have a,
Coach: Gosh, what's the other technology? It used to have an older radar originally. I've been working here almost 12 years.
Coach: And, we got the Trackman about 5 years ago, so we're into year 5 as far as, like, upgrading our tech.
Natalie Spiska: I see.
Coach: Pretty good, overview.
Natalie Spiska: And between the men's team and the women's team, would you say that technology, you guys share it? Is it the same?
Coach: Yeah, you know, the facility that we have here is for the men's and women's varsity golf teams, and every time we do an upgrade, it's in the context of both teams, so we share
Coach: It's not one team has it and the other one doesn't. It's a 50-50 split. And, so it gets a little crowded with 20 golfers, 10 women, 10, 10 men.
Natalie Spiska: Oh, wow, that's a lot.
Coach: But, because of the way the schedules, academic schedules are, not everybody can be here at the same time because of class schedules, so we make it work.
Natalie Spiska: Okay. You touched on it a little bit, but how has the use of technology in your program changed over the years?
Coach: I would say when I started coaching here in 2014, very few of the people on the, on the team utilized what we had. I'd say 2 or 3 out of the 10 would utilize the old,
Coach: radar system. I'm having a moment here, I cannot remember the name of it. No worries.
Coach: But once we got TrackMan, it was like this wholesale, upgrade. Everybody started using it. And then, when we got the simulator installed, now they can play virtual golf. So they can play a round of golf on a golf course, they can have
Coach: competitions with each other. I would say, you know, 5 years ago, we really transitioned from kind of, like, guys just hitting golf balls outside or hitting into a net, to really looking at the numbers, swing speed, ball speed,
Coach: spin rate, all those numbers that people can geek out about in the golf world. So, yeah, that's… it's definitely been a transition over the last 12 seasons.
Natalie Spiska: And are there any, like, particular skill areas that you think have the biggest impact from technology? Like, ball striking, short game?
Coach: Yeah, I would say that the short wedge… the wedges… the wedge game has definitely, improved more so than any other thing. You can hit drivers on the simulator and get… but… but your driver is your driver, and you… you… you're either on or you're not.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: The wedge…
Coach: Technology, being able to repeat the same kind of swing and know what an 80-yard wedge shot is, knowing what a 90 and a 100 and 120, those feelings that you have during the wintertime on the… on the simulator.
Coach: Quickly translate to green grass.
Coach: Not so much with the long irons and the drivers and the fairway woods, because those aren't as precise, if you will. So, the precision of the short game, and now putting, has really been a huge benefit to our team.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I was gonna ask if you think PuttView has helped with your team's putting as well, if you've seen any improvements.
Coach: Definitely. It's because you have break on your putt now, so the room, I'll describe it, is 30 feet long by 20 feet wide, and it used to just be a big, flat, green, synthetic turf with 10 holes. That gets a little boring in the wintertime to be putting on synthetic turf, because synthetic turf is not the same as grass. When you put slope to it, and half of it has
Coach: half the room now has slope to it with 5 holes. You can create
Coach: Any brake, left, right, hard break, soft brakes, uphill, downhill.
Coach: That has been a force multiplier for our improvement during the wintertime.
Natalie Spiska: And what is the biggest difference between your in-season and off-season prep? Like, obviously in the wintertime, you're gonna be indoors most of the time. Is that similar to how it is in the summer, or do you try and take advantage of being on grass in the summer?
Coach: Oh, we definitely take advantage of being outside, and one of the ways we mitigate the snow outside, because I'm sure the snow where you are now, and the snow…
Coach: So nobody's playing golf in, north of, north of [School Location] north. It's…
Coach: We travel early, so we went to [City 1] a couple weeks ago, we're going to [City 2] next week, and then we're gonna go to [City 3] in late March. So, we generally take 3…
Coach: cold weather trips to help prepare for the month of April. And the month of April is… I call it championship season, because at the end of April, we have our conference championships, and then the follow on the NCAAs, if we can make it. So, yeah, you go… you go warm early and often.
Coach: to get ready, because we didn't do that before. We, it wasn't until…
Coach: about 6 or 7 years ago, we started going south, and that showed a huge improvement in our ability to prepare for the April championship season.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's pretty similar for us as well, where April's also our conference, and yeah, we just came back, actually, yesterday from our first tournament. We were down in [University] tournament in [State].
Natalie Spiska: our flights got canceled because of the blizzard. We ended up staying a few extra days, so it felt like… felt like kind of a second spring break in a way, but yeah, I definitely agree that being able to be on grass is super important in those winter months, so…
Coach: How did you guys… how did you guys do in that tournament?
Natalie Spiska: Not too well, but obviously, like, coming back, it's pretty tough, usually, to just go from mats to grass, so I'm looking forward to the next tournament, though, to do better.
Coach: I was just gonna… I'm scrolling through scoreboard right now.
Natalie Spiska: Oh no
Coach: Haha.
Natalie Spiska: Put me on the spot. Let's just say one round really stood out, but.
Coach: Well, our girls just got back from, [Tournament] down in, [Location]. Oh, yeah. They played [University's] event down there, and it was brutal. It was cold.
Coach: It was windy, and the scores were, like, astronomically high, like, counting 88s and, you know, 85s, which they don't normally do, and .
Coach: our best golfer, [Player], she shot, like, 78, 79, 77, and she finished 3rd in the tournament.
Coach: Wow. Think about that, that just tells you what the conditions were, so…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, definitely. Are there any technologies you've tried to use and ended up not, like, implementing it and using it, and was there any reason for it?
Coach: Hmm.
Coach: So, [Coach 1] the women's coach, she's got… she's been a teaching pro for 30-plus years, and so she's got a lot of gadgets, and one of them, I can't think of the name of it, is, like, a little portable unit that you put… you can bring outside.
Coach: I would say some of the guys tried it, but, you know, they're defaulting to Trackman right now, and those units are kind of expensive for individual units, so,
Coach: There hasn't really been a lot of technology that we've…
Coach: gotten, not used, and, like, put on the back shelf. That's the only one I can think of, only because it's hers. The guys tried it, and they didn't like it as much as I like Trackman.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I understand that, especially since we just got a quad as well. Well, actually, a bushnell now, sorry. And yeah, I… it's nice to have, but I definitely think I would prefer the Trackman to it when possible.
Coach: Well, the TrackMan radar actually has two radars in it. One… one's dedicated to the swing, and the other's dedicated to ball flight. And I don't know if you know the background of TrackMan, but the… the technology comes from air defense radars, and a couple guys, I think in Sweden, they… their own… they took their own… they worked in the Swedish Air Force, and they took that technology and created…
Coach: the original Trackman, which was a single radar, doing both, both.
Coach: And now there's two. It's incredibly accurate, the technology, so…
Coach: If it can track a, you know, an F-15 going Mach 2, it can certainly track a golf ball going 180 miles an hour.
Coach: Yeah, so TrackMan has a range package. I don't know if you've heard of it, so it's like, basically, you can mount a, like, a flagpole on your range, and you have a radar up there, and it covers the entire range. So anybody hitting on the range can get that feedback with their cell phone, and they can link in with it. That's a little pricey, I wish we had that.
Coach: So that anybody on the range can just pull up their phone, look at it, and now they're working. They don't have to set up the portable Trackman. I would think that that's going to be our next step, because it basically allows anybody on the range to be using the same system. So it's a wide array. So Trackman, you set up behind one person, and they're hitting this golf ball. This is like a…
Coach: Call it, like, a…
Coach: a multi-track, man, where it watches the entire range and everybody that's hitting on it, so…
Coach: kind of cool technology, a bit pricey. I think the going rate is well over $100,000 for that unit, so we'll see. We'll see if we can raise the money.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's the only issue, is that I feel like some of these technologies are so cool, but definitely come with a high price tag.
Coach: Yeah, you need to find that, that, you know, alumni donor who doesn't.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: She doesn't mind donating a lot of money to help out the team.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, for sure. I just have two more questions left, so we'll wrap up quickly. What role do you see technology playing in collegiate golf in the next 5 to 10 years, and do you think it'll change the recruiting process in any way?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, the recruiting process now is such that if you don't have facilities and technologies when kids come to visit, you're gonna lose that kid unless that kid is absolutely, like, just gonna come to that school regardless. Like, maybe both his parents, or both her parents went to the school.
Coach: So, you have to have…
Coach: cutting-edge technology to keep up with the Joneses next door, you know, whatever school that is. You know, we're dealing, you know, we compete with [Rival Universities] for pretty much the same kind of kids. So, if you have the facility.
Coach: And the technology to go with it, then you're gonna get more of those, those, recruits.
Natalie Spiska: I know… I also spoke with the [University] coach, and he was speaking about how the combine is something that he's looking more at for the trackman. Was… is that something that you consider at all? The kid's like, my combine score is XYZ?
Coach: We use the combine score here to practice. Like, we'll say, okay, everybody's gonna hit the Combine this week, and see how their scores stack up nationally, but…
Coach: For a kid.
Coach: for me, recruiting a player, I'm gonna look at their junior golf record, their resume, the tournaments they play in, how many they play in, what their average finish, their, you know, their differential, and all that stuff.
Coach: You can sit there and really…
Coach: you could do a combine, and you didn't like your score, you could redo the combine. You can keep doing it. It's like playing a video game. You get better at it the more times you do it. So, if a kid sends me a high combine score, I'm like, yeah, he might have a trackman in his basement, and him and his buddies are doing it, you know, day in and day out. That's not as important to me as going and watching them play on the golf course, watching their process.
Coach: making sure that they're not a lunatic when they're on the golf course, like, you know, going crazy, getting mad, throwing clubs. Those are more important milestones for me in the recruiting process. I can tell if a kid's got a good swing.
Coach: And when they sit down and talk to me here in the office with their parents, I'm evaluating them, I'm evaluating their mom and dad, you know, are they going to be a good fit for our program?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's some really good insight, because, yeah, even though you have the technology, it's important to not be overly reliant on it at the same time.
Coach: Exactly.
Natalie Spiska: And yeah, final question. Overall, would you say the technology just had a positive or negative impact on your program?
Coach: especially during the wintertime, definitely positive, because I feel like you can go down a rabbit hole with technology, and you get worked up about the minutiae, but…
Coach: during the wintertime, when the option is hitting into a net in a square room, or hitting into a simulator screen that's giving you feedback immediately on your ball flight, definitely there's more positives than to the negatives. And if I see a kid kind of going off the rails, like, I'll say, just go play. Let's just go play golf on the golf course. So you got the range, you got short game, you got putting, and you got golf
Coach: of course, and then you have indoor stuff, so the sooner we transition to the outdoor game and just playing
Coach: A lot of golf.
Coach: Then going back to technology when you need it, but not getting so wrapped around the axle with technology that it hinders your ability to just go play.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I think Jessica Korda said it, where she's like, my biggest advice to young players is to just play, which, yeah, at the end of the day, you're just playing, so you should practice what you, what you do. Alright, I'll stop recording.
Coach: Okay.